Joseph Cornell
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Joseph Cornell Estate Papers, circa 1911, 1944-1986, Series 10:; (boxes 19-22; 3.5 linear feet)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1986, 10.1:
    - Valparaiso University, 1977-1982, (2 folders) (Box 21, Folder 35-36)
    - Viking Press, 1974-1975 (Box 21, Folder 37)
    - von Furstenberg, Betsy, 1973, 1980, undated (Box 21, Folder 38)
    - Vondrak, Deanna Mayer, 1975-1983 (Box 21, Folder 39)
    - V, 1973 (Box 21, Folder 40)
    - Waldman, Diane, 1976-1977, 1981-1982 (Box 21, Folder 41)
    - Washburn Gallery, 1973-1983 (Box 21, Folder 42)
    - Washington University in St. Louis, 1981-1982, (2 folders) (Box 21, Folder 43-44)
    - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1977-1979 (Box 21, Folder 45)
    - Williams College Museum of Art, 1973-1976 (Box 21, Folder 46)
    - Windham, Donald, 1975 (Box 21, Folder 47)
    - Wolff, Ted, 1981 (Box 21, Folder 48)
    - W, 1973-1981 (Box 21, Folder 49)
    - Z, 1975-1978 (Box 21, Folder 50)
  - Legal Files, 1966-1968, 1973-1983, 10.2:
    Subseries is comprised of Benton's files pertaining to various legal matters that arose in the course of administering Cornell's residual estate. Files primarily consist of copies of correspondence sent and received by Benton's lawyer, Dennis Hurley (of the firm, Behringer, Hurley and Hurley), on her behalf; copies of legal documents such as briefs, exhibits, court reporter's minutes, petitions, affidavits, and compromise agreements; and copies of income tax returns.
    Files primarily relate to the legal dispute between the executors of Cornell's estate (Richard Ader and Wayne Andrews) and members of Cornell's family (namely, Benton and her niece, Helen Batcheller). The main issue of dispute was the ownership of Cornell art works in the possession of family members. Also at issue was the ownership of the non-Cornell art works owned by Cornell, as well as whether or not certain Cornell material (such as source material and ephemera) was to be considered art work (since art works went to the Trust and remaining material went to Benton as part of the residual estate). Files also relate to the case in United States Tax Court, determining whether the value of the works transferred to Benton and Batcheller were includable within the gross estate of Cornell for federal estate tax purposes.
    To a lesser extent, files (especially correspondence) also relate to the estate tax proceedings of the Helen S. Cornell estate (See also Series 1); the issue of ownership of the Bebe Marie doll (which initially belonged to Cornell's cousin, Ethel Storms, and was subsequently used by Cornell in the box, Untitled (Bebe Marie), in the 1940s); the charitable trust, the C and B (Cornell and Benton) Foundation, that Benton established as part of the compromise agreement with the executors; payment of gift taxes on works owned by Batcheller; and the appraisal, insurance and loan of Cornell works owned by Benton.
    Files are arranged, more or less, chronologically. Material in the files is arranged in rough reverse chronological order as that seems to have been how Benton typically compiled it.
    - Helen S. Cornell Estate Papers, 1966-1968, (4 folders) (Box 21, Folder 51-54)
    - Case Re: Joseph Cornell Estate, 1973-1974, (6 folders) (Box 21, Folder 55-60)
    - Case Re: Joseph Cornell Estate, 1973-1974, (2 folders) (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
    - Case Re: Joseph Cornell Estate, Betty Cornell Benton's Notes, 1973-1974, undated (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Case Re: Joseph Cornell Estate, Correspondence between Lawyers, 1976-1976 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Case Re: Joseph Cornell Estate, Correspondence with Special Investigations, 1974 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Case Re: Joseph Cornell Estate, Correspondence with Potential Witnesses, 1974-1975 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Case Re: Joseph Cornell Estate, Partial Synopsis of Testimony on Behalf of Elizabeth C. Benton, undated (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Case Re: Joseph Cornell Estate, Compromise Agreement, 1974-1976 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Case Re: Joseph Cornell Estate, Settlement, 1975 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, General, 1973-1977 (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence re: Bebe Marie, 1974-1978 (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence with Fourcade, Droll Inc., 1975 (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence re: Income, Estate, and Gift Taxes, 1975-1977 (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - Cornell and Benton Foundation, 1975-1980, (4 folders) (Box 22, Folder 14-17)
    - Case in United States Tax Court, Motion to Intervene, 1978 (Box 22, Folder 18)
    - Case in United States Tax Court, Response to Informal Request for a "Discovery List," 1981, (3 folders) (Box 22, Folder 19-21)
    - Case in United States Tax Court, 1983 (Box 22, Folder 22)
  - Printed Material, 1944-1982, 10.3:
    Subseries is comprised of printed material, some of which was most likely collected by Cornell and either shared with his sister during his lifetime or bequeathed to her along with the rest of his papers, and some of which was created and/or accumulated by Benton during the time she was administering Cornell's residual estate.
    Printed material collected by Cornell includes various clippings, a legal publication, issues of National Geographic magazine (with pages cut out), and stamps. It is possible that some of this printed material (particularly the magazines) constitutes part of Cornell's source material, which he may have used in his own box constructions and collages or shared with Benton for her to use in her collages.
    Printed material collected by Benton includes announcements and catalogs for exhibitions of Cornell works; clippings on or related to Cornell; publications (such as Architectural Digest and Bulletin of the Art Institute of Chicago) with articles on or referencing Cornell or his art works; lists (created by Benton) of Cornell material given to the Anthology Film Archives and of Cornell's record collection (parts of which seem to have been given to different institutions, including the Lighthouse Music School, the New York Institute for the Education of the Blind, and Southampton College, among others); and a brief biography of Robert Cornell written by Lynda Roscoe Hartigan for the International Year of Disabled Persons at the Smithsonian Institution.
    Files are arranged in chronological order.
    - Printed Material Collected by Cornell, Miscellaneous, 1944-1971 (Box 22, Folder 23)
    - Printed Material Collected by Cornell, Clippings on Stamps, 1954, 1959 (Box 22, Folder 24)
    - Printed Material Collected by Cornell, National Geographic Magazines, 1956-1957, (2 folders) (Box 22, Folder 25-26)
    - Printed Material Collected by Cornell, Stamps, undated, (6 folders) (Box 22, Folder 27-32)
    - Exhibition Announcements, 1966, 1982 (Box 22, Folder 33)
    - Clippings on Comet Kohoutek, 1973 (Box 22, Folder 34)
    - Exhibition Catalogs, 1974-1978 (Box 22, Folder 35)
    - Clippings on or related to Cornell, 1974-1983 (Box 22, Folder 36)
    - Publications with articles on or referencing Cornell, 1977-1982, (2 folders) (Box 22, Folder 37-38)
    - Lists of Cornell Material Given to Anthology Film Archives, 1976-1977 (Box 22, Folder 39)
    - Robert Cornell Biography by Lynda Roscoe Hartigan, 1981 (Box 22, Folder 40)
    - Lists of Cornell's Record Collection, undated (Box 22, Folder 41)
    - Newspaper Clippings, undated (Box 22, Folder 42)
  - Miscellaneous Family Papers, circa 1911, 1944-1964, 10.4:
    Subseries consists of fragments of the papers of Betty Cornell Benton and Helen S. Cornell.
    Betty Cornell Benton's papers include kindergarten art work, a printed inventory of Robert Cornell's train collection (which she compiled in collaboration with Robert during the time period from 1962 to 1963), and notes. Some of Benton's notes concern Cornell's biography and magazine collection, and may relate to certain activities in handling his estate.
    Helen S. Cornell's papers include printed material on Flushing and the World's Fair (which took place in Flushing in 1939), as well as some writings. The printed material, collected and oftentimes annotated by Mrs. Cornell, documents some of the interests she shared with her son and relates to certain formative experiences shared by the family (such as their repeated visits to the World's Fair, which seems to have been a special time for all).
    Beyond the fact that they were stored together, it is unclear how the rest of these fragments relate to Cornell's estate papers. Related papers can be found amongst biographical material, family correspondence, and Robert Cornell's papers.
    - Betty Cornell Benton Papers, Kindergarten Art Work, circa 1911 (Box 22, Folder 43)
    - Betty Cornell Benton Papers, Inventory of Robert Cornell's Train Collection, 1962-1963, undated (Box 22, Folder 44)
    - Betty Cornell Benton Papers, Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Box 22, Folder 45)
    - Betty Cornell Benton Papers, Notes on Cornell Biography, undated (Box 22, Folder 46)
    - Helen S. Cornell Papers, Printed Material on World's Fair, 1939-1940 (Box 22, Folder 47)
    - Helen S. Cornell Papers, Printed Material on Flushing, 1944-1949, 1957, undated (Box 22, Folder 48)
    - Helen S. Cornell Papers, Writings, 1952-1964, undated (Box 22, Folder 49)
- Robert Cornell Papers, 1924-1965, Series 11:; (boxes 24, 28; 0.4 linear feet)
  Series consists of the personal papers of Cornell's younger brother, Robert, nicknamed Snicky. Even though he suffered from cerebral palsy and was confined to a wheelchair for most of his life, Robert led an active and creative life, pursuing hobbies such as drawing, train collecting, and short wave radio, and sharing many of Cornell's interests such as music, films, and Christian Science. Stemming from his creative activities and interests, and his close relationships with family members, his papers include correspondence received by him (See Series 2 for correspondence written by him), writings, art works, printed material, photographs, notes, QSL cards (which are traded amongst amateur radio operators), financial material such as his financial diary and receipts, address book, and his last will and testament.
  It is possible that either Cornell kept Robert's papers amongst his own or that Benton placed Robert's papers in with Cornell's in the course of preparing them for donation. However Robert's papers came to be included amongst Cornell's, it most likely is not an accident. Both Cornell and Benton were concerned with how Robert would be remembered. This concern is reflected in Cornell's use of Robert's drawings in his series of memorial collages and in Benton's expressed tendency to include one of Robert's drawings (usually a copy) when loaning or donating Cornell art works (See copy of letters to Aline Porter in Subseries 10.1). The fact that Robert's papers can be found amongst Cornell's can be interpreted as part of the family's effort to foster Robert's memory.
  The Robert Cornell Papers are arranged alphabetically according to format. The bulk of this series has been scanned; typically only covers, title pages, and/or relevant pages of printed material such as magazines and exhibition catalogs for artists other than Cornell, have been scanned.
  - Address Book, circa 1956-1961 (Box 24 (hol), Folder 1)
    Includes notes, and clippings and stamps pasted inside.
  - Art Work, "Coin de Chambre" (framed watercolor), circa 1963, (See Box 28) (Box 24 (hol), Folder 2)
  - Art Work, Drawings from Mouse King Series, 1958, 1960 (Box 24 (hol), Folder 3)
  - Family Correspondence, Nell Benton, 1936-1963, undated (Box 24 (hol), Folder 4)
  - Family Correspondence, Helen S. Cornell, 1946-1964 (Box 24 (hol), Folder 5)
  - Family Correspondence, Joseph Cornell, 1952, 1965, undated (Box 24 (hol), Folder 6)
  - Financial Diary, 1963-1965 (Box 24 (hol), Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, Bedside Network, 1959-1964 (Box 24 (hol), Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, Christian Science Monitor, 1943 (Box 24 (hol), Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence, Tony Curtis, 1964 (Box 24 (hol), Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence, Miscellaneous, 1937-1965, undated (Box 24 (hol), Folder 11)
  - Inventories, Model Train Catalogues and Magazines, 1962, undated (Box 24 (hol), Folder 12)
  - Last Will and Testament, 1964 (Box 24 (hol), Folder 13)
  - Notes, 1961-1963, undated (Box 24 (hol), Folder 14)
  - Photographs, First Westhampton Vacation, 1951 (Box 24 (hol), Folder 15)
  - Printed Material, Clippings on Model Trains, 1947-1948, 1957 (Box 24 (hol), Folder 16)
  - Printed Material, Publications, 1930-1935, 1963 (Box 24 (hol), Folder 17)
  - QSL Cards, 1940-1948, undated (Box 24 (hol), Folder 18)
  - Receipts, 1959-1964 (Box 24 (hol), Folder 19)
  - Writings, Various, 1924-1925 (Box 24 (hol), Folder 20)
  - Writings, "The Royal Recorder," 1928 (Box 24 (hol), Folder 21)
  - Writings, "Succor" (typescript), 1931 (Box 24 (hol), Folder 22)
  - Writings, "Dream of circa Oct. 12", 1964 (Box 24 (hol), Folder 23)
  - Writings, Untitled Essay on Radio (typescript), undated (Box 24 (hol), Folder 24)
  - Oversized, Art Work, "Coin de Chambre" (framed watercolor), circa 1963, (See Box 24, F2) (Box 28 (sol))